Register of the Museum of Russian Culture Manuscript Collection
Hoover Institution Archives
Museum of Russian Culture manuscript collection,
1869-1990
2001C47
12 microfilm reels (1.8 linear feet)
Hoover Institution on War, Revolution, and Peace Stanford, California 94305-6010
Miscellaneous diaries, memoirs, studies, and other writings, by various Russian and Russian émigré writers, relating to Russian history and culture, Russian participation in World War I, the Russian Revolution and Civil War, and Russian émigré affairs. Collected by the Museum of Russian Culture, San Francisco.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for research.
Acquisition Information
Acquired.
Location of Originals
Originals in: Museum of Russian Culture, San Francisco.
Scope and Content Note
This collection contains individual holographs and typescripts (with occasional associated correspondence) donated either directly to the Museum or submitted to Russkaia zhizn' and subsequently deposited in the Museum. Most of the materials are in Russian or English, and include fiction, memoirs, and article- or book-length studies on historical, political, or social themes. The earliest manuscripts, though undated, are Nestor Kukol'nik's "Tolkovanie Evangeliia," and a series of lives of Russian saints (unidentified author), followed by Archbishop Nikolai of Japan's (Nikolai Kasatkin) "Iaponiia s tochki zreniia Khristianskoi missii" (1869).
Detailed processing and preservation microfilming for these materials were made possible by a generous grant from the National Endowment for the Humanities and by matching funds from the Hoover Institution and Museum of Russian Culture. The grant also provides depositing a microfilm copy in the Hoover Institution Archives. The original materials remain in the Museum of Russian Culture, San Francisco as its property. A transfer table indicating corresponding box and reel numbers is available at the Hoover Institution Archives.
The Hoover Institution assumes all responsibility for notifying users that they must comply with the copyright law of the United States (Title 17 United States Code) and Hoover Rules for the Use and Reproduction of Archival Materials.
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the repository's online public access catalog.
Subjects
Russia--History.; Russia--Civilization.; World War, 1914-1918--Russia.; Soviet Union--History--Revolution, 1917-1921.; Russians in foreign countries.; Russia.; Soviet Union.; World War, 1914-1918.
Other Index Terms Related to this Collection
Museum of Russian Culture (San Francisco, Calif.)
Series Description
- Manuscripts, 1869-1990. (Box 1-9)
  Articles, books, diaries and memoirs arranged alphabetically by author - and chronologically by title therein - with unidentified and anonymous works, arranged alphabetically by title, preceding others
Container List
- MANUSCRIPTS, 1869-1990 (Box 1)
  - Unidentified
    - Notes on Russian military history, n.d. (Folder 1: 1)
      Holograph and typescript
    - "Pochestnyi pir u kniazia Vladimira-Krasnogo Solnyshka," 1926. (Folder 1: 2)
      Typescript (play)
    - Series of lives of Russian saints, composed apparently some time in the mid-19th century, with a letter from Archbishop Ioann (Shakhovskoi) to A. A. Sollogub, 1983, describing their provenance, n.d. (Folder 1: 3)
    - Series of writings on Russian history and culture, including article on Nicholas I and on Russian songs, 1983. (Folder 1: 4)
      Holograph. Also includes photograph of unidentified individuals
    - "Spetsial'nye terminy i vyrazheniia lagernikov Solovetskogo lageria," n.d. (Folder 1: 5)
      Holograph
    - "Vospominaniia o krushenii tsarskago poiezda bliz stantsii Borki 17-go oktiabria 1888 goda," n.d. (Folder 1: 6)
      Typescript
  - A., Colonel, "Portret Imperatritsy," and other sketches of military life, n.d. (Folder 1: 7)
  - Aattonen, "Ingermanlandiia," n.d. (Folder 1: 8)
  - Albus, "Dreams: Psikhologicheskii etiud," n.d. (Folder 1: 9)
  - Alekhin, S.
    - "Nemonarkhist o monarkhii," 1985 June 4. (Folder 1: 10)
    - "Vlasovskoe dvizhenie i voina s kommunizmom," 1983 August 30. (Folder 1: 11)
  - Aleksandrovskii, G., "Russkaia emigratsiia v Chekhoslovakii," n.d. (Folder 1: 12)
  - Andrets, N., "Skitaniia po Evrope," 1949. (Folder 1: 13)
  - Antonov, V., See Pranskevich, A.
  - Averchenko, Arkadii, "Entsiklopedicheskii slovar'," n.d. (Folder 1: 14)
  - Balakan (?), untitled short story in letter form, 1949 January 27. (Folder 1: 15)
  - Barkalov, L., "Byt' ili ne byt'," n.d. (Folder 1: 16)
  - Berin-Bey, Boris, "Yksitiosta ja puoli vuotta Stalinin paratiisissa 1945-1956," [1957]. (Folder 1: 17)
  - Bigaev, N. (Box 2)
    - "Kharakteristika russkago naroda," n.d. (Folder 2: 1)
    - "Rossiiskaia Imperiia-Kontinent," n.d. (Folder 2: 2)
  - Bodisco, M. A., "Fortifikatsiia v sovremennoi voine i eia znachenie," 1931 February 15. (Folder 2: 3)
  - Bogacheva-Baskakova, E. V., untitled memoirs of life in Pushkin, USSR, under Nazi occupation, 1941-1944, [1969]. (Folder 2: 4)
  - Bolotina, Kleopatra, "V'iuga," n.d. (Folder 2: 5)
  - Brovtsyn, B., "Stopiatidesiatiletiie so dnia osnovaniia Imperatorskogo Uchilishcha Pravovedeniia," [1985]. (Folder 2: 6)
  - Chedanov, V. G., "Zakon deistviia slozhnogo rychaga," [1933]. (Folder 2: 7)
    Typescript. Includes diagram and attachment
  - Chernigovets, open letter to Alexander Solzhenitsyn, 1974 February 16. (Folder 2: 8)
  - Chertkov, Georgii, "Tam, gde vossiial miru svet razuma," 1977 December 29. (Folder 2: 9)
  - Davydov, Boris, "Nedra satany: Povest'-satira," 1966. (Folder 2: 10)
  - Deepe, Joan, "The Russians in San Francisco," 1981 May. (Folder 2: 11)
  - Dobrovol'skii-Zavadskoi, N. A., "Zhizn' v Evropie:Eia trevogi i upovaniia," lecture read before the Obshchestvo zashchity russkogo rebenka, San Francisco, California, 1947 September 22. (Folder 2: 12)
  - Dobuzhinskii, M., "Nautilus," n.d. (Folder 2: 13)
  - Dubrovskii, A. P., "Otverzhennye i obrechennye," 1982. (Folder 2: 14)
  - Egorov, K. D., "Mamino kreslo," n.d. (Folder 2: 15)
  - F-n, A., "Germaniia ot denezhnoi reformy do segodniashnego dnia," n.d. (Folder 2: 16)
  - Fe, Eduard von, diary and field-book, 1915-1918. (Folder 2: 17)
    Holograph (Fe was a subaltern in the 3rd company of the First Turkestan Sapper Battalion)
  - Fedin, untitled thoughts on historical and philosophical issues and Russia's place in the march of civilization, n.d. (Folder 2: 18)
  - Fedorov, N. V., "Fakty iz istorii Imperatorskoi Rossii," n.d. (Folder 2: 19)
  - Fedorov, Nikolai, "Nasushchnaia zadacha emigratsii," 1949 March 10. (Folder 2: 20)
  - Fedorova, Nina, The Family, 1940. (Box-folder 3: 1)
  - Fokskroft, Elizaveta Grigor'evna, "Obitel' pod Parizhem," n.d. (Folder 3: 2)
  - Gladstone, Michael, "Rozhdestvo Khristovo v Amerike," 1949 December 26. (Folder 3: 3)
    Holograph (poem)
  - Golovachev, Mstislav Petrovich, "Rol' rossiiskoi emigratsii v sovremennykh usloviiakh," lecture delivered before the Ob"edinennaia Russko-Amerikanskaia assotsiatsiia, San Francisco, California, 1956 February 19. (Folder 3: 4)
  - Grinenko, V. Kh., "O zabluzhdeniiakh i posliedstviiakh," 1960. (Folder 3: 5)
    Typescript (relates to Russian émigré monarchism)
  - Grinevich, Ivan, "Na Paskhie," and two other short sketches, n.d. (Folder 3: 6)
  - Iashnova, O., "Poezdka v Solovetskii monastyr' v 1915 g.," 1954 November 22. (Folder 3: 7)
  - Karamzin, Aleksandr Aleksandrovich, "Egor Petrovich Zhant'ev (Sirkiska)," 1915(?) January 4. (Folder 3: 8)
    Holograph (fragment of memoirs)
  - Kartashev, Anton, "Dukhovnaia shkola v Rossii," 1947 August 14. (Folder 3: 9)
  - Kasatkin, Nikolai., See Nikolai, Archbishop of Japan
  - Korchevskoi, I., "Russkii iazyk," n.d. (Folder 3: 10)
  - Kosarev, A. P., "Tragediia osvobozhdennykh i vernuvshikhsia," 1952. (Folder 3: 11)
  - Kropotov, E. A., "Voprosy novieishago sel'skago khoziaistva," n.d. (Folder 3: 12)
  - Kube, Mikhail Oskarovich, "Kratkii ocherk istorii russkogo flota," 1947. (Folder 4: 2)
  - Kukol'nik, Nestor Vasil'evich, "Tolkovanie Evangeliia," n.d. (Folder 4: 3)
  - Larin, G., "Vtoraia chast' doklada 'Monarkhiia ili Respublika'," n.d. (Folder 4: 4)
  - Lavrova, Nadia, "Professors," 1934 May. (Folder 4: 5)
  - Le Heart, Avenir
    - "Photographic Composition," n.d. (Folder 4: 6)
    - "Astralida: Little Princess of Heaven," 1940. (Folder 4: 7)
    - Coloring Photographs in Oil and Water Colors, 1945. (Folder 4: 8)
      Printed copy
  - Levenets, Boris Vladimirovich, "Russkaia armiia na Rumynskom fronte v 1916 godu," 1916 December. (Folder 4: 9)
    Holograph. Includes attached correspondence, biographical note and inserts
  - Levitskii, E. L. "Fevral'skie dni," n.d. (Folder 4: 10)
    Typescript. Includes attached poem
  - Liusta (Box 5)
    - "Iz sovetskoi deistvitel'nosti," n.d. (Folder 5: 1)
    - "Sovetskaia deistvitel'nost': Inostrantsy v Sovetskoi Rossii," n.d. (Folder 5: 2)
  - Luknitskii, Vladimir Vsevolodovich, "Ukhod za granitsu:zhizn' za rubezhom," n.d. (Folder 5: 3-4)
    Typescript (life in Shanghai, 1922-1946)
  - Maevskii, Vl.
    - "Gosudarevy sapery," n.d. (Folder 5: 5)
    - "Po povodu narekanii," n.d. (Folder 5: 6)
  - Maksimov, Nikolai, "Chto takoe bol'shevizm," n.d. (Folder 5: 7)
  - Maleevskii, V. A. "Velikii kniaz' Kirill Vladimirovich i kniaz' Vladimir Kirillovich," 1977 June 15. (Folder 5: 8)
  - Mariian, N., "Iz istorii Vtoroi mirovoi voiny na odesskikh rubezhakh," n.d. (Folder 5: 9)
  - Mashevskii, K. P., "Moi vospominaniia o gimnazii i SPb Gornom institutie," 1969 January. (Folder 5: 10)
  - Mashevskii, N. P., "Tak bylo: Istoriia odnoi liubvi," 1922 June. (Folder 5: 11)
  - Matveeva, Kapitolina N.
    - "Taiga gorit," 1944 November 3. (Folder 5: 12)
    - "Slu-u-u-sha-a-ai!" 1944 November 10. (Folder 5: 13)
  - Meier, Mariia Fedorovna (?), "The Great American Secret," n.d. (Folder 5: 14)
    Holograph. Includes attached photographs
  - Miasnitskii, I. I., "Syshchik:Original'naia komediia-fars v 3-kh deist.," n.d. (Box-folder 6: 1)
  - Milenko, G. L., "Staraia russkaia advokatura i N. P. Karabchevskii," n.d. (Folder 6: 2)
  - Miller, K. K.
    - "Angliiskii opyt," n.d. (Folder 6: 3)
    - "Diela evropeiskiia," n.d. (Folder 6: 4)
  - Mishunin, Nikolai, "Nishchenka," 1949 January. (Folder 6: 5)
  - Moiseev, G. M., "Letopis' beloi sem'i," 1982. (Folder 6: 6)
    Typescript. Includes attached photographs and correspondence, and two brief sketches
  - Monkevich, Viktor I., "Dvadtsat' dnei na transporte 'General Sturgis':Iz dnevnika zhurnalista," 1949. (Folder 6: 7)
  - Muravin, Viktor Romanovich, "Potomok Ermaka:Roman," 1985. (Folder 6: 8)
    Typescript. Includes attached poems
  - Nalbandov, Vladimir, "Zamietka k voprosu o polozhenii prodovol'stviia v Krymu v 1918 i 1920 gg.," 1948 August 11. (Folder 6: 9)
  - Nelidova-Fiveiskaia, Lidiia, "A. S. Griboedov," 1945 July 4. (Folder 6: 10)
  - Nikitina, Sofiia
    - "Svetloi pamiati moei materi Ol'gi Pavlovny Churkinoi," 1967. (Folder 6: 11)
    - "Istoriia moei zhizni: Kniga piataia," 1970. (Folder 6: 12)
  - Nikolai, Archbishop of Japan (Nikolai Kasatkin), "Iaponiia s tochki zreniia Khristianskoi missii," Russkii viestnik, 1869 September. (Folder 6: 13)
  - Oriol', Elena, "Niania," 1946. (Folder 6: 14)
  - Pavlov, Leonid, Tebe, Andreevskii flag, 1977. (Folder 6: 15)
    Typescript. Includes material not printed in the published edition
  - Pavlyuk, Ivan, "A Kulak," n.d. (Folder 7: 2)
  - Ploss, Taisiia, "Nasha semeinaia khronika," 1963. (Folder 7: 3)
  - Podstavina, G. G., "Moi pedagogicheskii put'," 1970 April 19. (Folder 7: 4)
  - Popov, K., "V Zarubiezhnom soiuzie invalidov," n.d. (Folder 7: 5)
  - Porokhovshchikov, P. S. (pseud. - P. Sergieich), "Pushkin za sovietskim rubezhom," n.d. (Folder 7: 6)
  - Pranskevich, Anton (pseud. - V. Antonov), "Neofitsial'noe iskusstvo v Rossii," 1985. (Folder 7: 7)
  - Pravoslavnyi, "Eshche o Pravoslavii," 1949 August. (Folder 7: 8)
  - Prigodina, Iuliia
    - "Gornopromyshlennyi Iug Rossii v semidesiatykh godakh proshlago vieka," n.d. (Folder 7: 9)
    - "Mater'ialy po elektrifikatsii Donetskago basseina," n.d. (Folder 7: 10)
  - Raiskii, Nikolai., See Rikhter, Nikolai
  - Rikhter, Nikolai (pseud. - N. Raiskii), "Krasnyi Dekan ili dukhovnyi predatel'," 1949 April 25. (Folder 7: 11)
  - Rubanov, Lev Stepanovich, "Klub 'Mednyi vsadnik'," Mosty, 1967. (Folder 7: 12)
  - Samarin, Vladimir, "Ocherki rossiiskoi emigratsii," n.d. (Folder 7: 13)
  - Sergieich, P., See Porokhovshchikov, P. S.
  - Severianin, A., See Znamenskii, A.
  - Sh., B. "Kto zhe oni? (Zapiski podsovetskogo reportera)," n.d. (Folder 7: 14)
  - Sheremet'ev, Mikhail Nikolaevich, "Kratkiia zamietki po istorii Drevnei Rusi," n.d. (Folder 7: 15)
  - Sibashko, T., "Mrachnye gody," 1990. (Folder 7: 16)
  - Smirnova-Maksheeva, T., "O Svetleishei kniagine Iur'evskoi," n.d. (Folder 7: 17)
  - Snezhin, B., See Sokolov, B. A.
  - Sofronov, S.
    - "Mongoliia i aziatskiia narody S.S.S.R.," n.d. (Folder 7: 18)
    - Pervyi piatiletnii plan, 1929-1935 gg.," n.d. (Folder 7: 19)
    - "Vragi Rossii vneshnie i vnutrennie vtoroi poloviny deviatnadtsatogo stoletiia," n.d. (Folder 7: 20)
    - "Vypiska iz knigo Konstantina Emel'ianova chudom perezhil Nikolaevskuiu rezniu," n.d. (Folder 7: 21)
  - Sokharev, Vasilii Kuzmich, "Altaisko-Kolumbiiskaia paseka," 1940 February. (Folder 7: 22)
    Typescript. Includes attached photographs
  - Sokoloff, Valentin A., "The Last Links," 1987 January 31. (Box-folder 8: 1)
    Typescript (memoirs)
  - Sokolov, B. A. (pseud. - B. Snezhin), "Chto takoe kosmopolitizm," n.d. (Folder 8: 2)
  - Stenbock-Fermor, Ivan, "Memoirs of Ivan Count Stenbock-Fermor," 1976 December. (Folder 8: 3)
  - Stepanov, Nikolai, "11 s ½ liet v Stalinskom 'raiu'," [1976]. (Folder 9: 2)
  - Stogov, P. E., "Novaia elektro-dinamicheskaia gipoteza," n.d. (Folder 9: 3)
  - Tarasov, A. A., "Energiia, kak edinaia substantsiia vselennoi," n.d. (Folder 9: 4)
  - Tarsaidze, A. G., "'Otstalaia' Rossiia," n.d. (Folder 9: 5)
  - Teffi, N. (N. Lokhvitskaia), "Skazka," n.d. (Folder 9: 6)
  - Tishchenko, N., "Velikoe pereselenie slavian," 1974. (Folder 9: 7)
  - Tul'chinskii, K. N., "Doklad Gornago Inzhenera K. N. Tul'chinskago Kolonizatsionnomu Sovieshchaniiu," 1919 January 17. (Folder 9: 8)
  - Uralov, S. A., "Arkadii Arkanov: Roman," 1948 May 12. (Folder 9: 9)
  - Vagin, E., "Chto sluchilos' s Bibliotekoi im. Gogolia v Rime?" 1984 January 2. (Folder 9: 10)
  - Valentinova, Aleksandra (pseud. of N. A. Tsitovich?), "Krest'ianskaia reforma Tsaria-Osvoboditelia i ee istoricheskie puti," [1948]. (Folder 9: 11)
  - Vasilaki, Vladimir (pseud. - Nikolai Vasilevskii), "Sluchai so studentom:Rasskaz iz sovetskoi zhizni," n.d. (Folder 9: 12)
  - Vasilevskii, Nikolai., See Vasilaki, Vladimir
  - Voitenkov, N., "Tsar' i poet," n.d. (Folder 10: 1)
  - Vostokov, Vladimir, Rev.
    - "Posliedniee moe kochev'e mezhdu Moskvoi i dachei v Gorkakh i ot Moskvy do Odessy," n.d. (Folder 10: 2)
    - "Vopli tserkovnye na Vserossiiskom Tserkovnom Soborie v Moskvie 22 i 22 ianvaria 1918 g.," 1951 June 15. (Folder 10: 3)
    - "Svietil'nik, siiavshii pri napisanii knigi Rozy i shipy," 1952 June 24. (Folder 10: 4)
  - Vysheslavtsev, B. P., editor and author of introduction, "Otkrovennye rasskazy strannika dukhovnomu svoemu ottsu," 1933. (Folder 10: 5)
  - Zauer, L., "Voprosy zhizni i smerti v izlozhenii mudrykh liudei," [1953]. (Folder 10: 6)
  - Zavalishin, B., "Nieskol'ko slov o natsional'nom edinstvie, o tvorchestvie i o russkom rebenkie," 1946 July 15. (Folder 10: 7)
  - Zhernakova-Nikolaeva, Aleksandra, "Dvie sud'by," n.d. (Folder 10: 8)
  - Zimin, T.
    - "Gospod' porugaem ne byvaet," n.d. (Folder 10: 9)
    - "Klikushi," n.d. (Folder 10: 10)
    - "Ob osvobozhdenii Rossii," n.d. (Folder 10: 11)
    - "Okhota na khishchnykh zvierei v Rossii," n.d. (Folder 10: 12)
    - "Rol' politsii pri upravlenii Gosudarstvom i neobkhodimost' politsii pri dieistvuiushchei armii," n.d. (Folder 10: 13)
  - Znamenskii, A. (pseud. - A. Severianin)
    - "Dva narkoma," n.d. (Folder 10: 14)
    - "Iz vospominanii ob utrachennoi rodine," n.d. (Folder 10: 15)
    - "Kratkaia spravka dlia istorika antibol'shevitskogo dvizheniia v Rossii," n.d. (Folder 10: 16)
    - "Nemtsy," n.d. (Folder 10: 17)
    - "Voina," n.d. (Folder 10: 18)